Finding Aid for the Thomas Daniel Young Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Thomas Daniel Young Collection
2016
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0538
4.59 linear feet
Scope and Content Note
The largest part of the collection consists of Xerox copies and page proofs of Dr. Young’s books: The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate (1974); The New Criticism and After (1977); and Gentleman in a Dustcoat (1976). This section also contains the longhand copy of Dr. Young’s Gentleman in a Dustcoat: A Biography of John Crowe Ransom.
Another part of the collection contains Research Materials, consisting of Xerox copies of the voluminous correspondence between John Crowe Ransom and family members as well as professional colleagues. These letters range in date from before World War I up to the 1970s.
There’s only one file of correspondence between Dr. Young and others, but within that file is an original letter from Flannery O’Connor. She had written to John Crowe Ransom about her work in her story A Circle of Fire, and he had enclosed that letter in his correspondence with Professor Young. (See Box 1, File 1)
Biography
Thomas Daniel Young was born October 22,1919 in Louisville, Mississippi. He received his B.A. from the University of Southern Mississippi, His M.A. from the University of Mississippi, and his Ph.D. from Vanderbilt in 1950. At Vanderbilt he studied with Donald Davidson and Richmond Beatty.
During World War II, Young served in the Army Air Corps (1942-1945), stationed in England for part of that time.
He taught Southern Literature and American Literature at the University of Southern Mississippi from 1950-1957 and Delta State University from 1957-1961, where he also served as Dean.
In 1961 Young came to Vanderbilt as Director of Undergraduate Admissions and also Associate Professor of English. Later he was an assistant to the Vice-Chancellor. From 1963-1973, he served as Chairman of the English Department, and in 1972 he was named the first recipient of the Gertrude Conaway Vanderbilt Professorship of English. Dr. Young retired from Vanderbilt in 1985.
Dr. Young was the author of 25 books and almost two hundred articles. Among his works are: The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate; The New Criticism and After; John Crowe Ransom: An Annotated Bibliography; The Lytle-Tate Letters; and Fabulous Provinces: A Memoir. His authorized biography of John Crowe Ransom, Gentleman in a Dustcoat won the Jules F. Landry Award. In 1952-1953 Dr. Young served as President of the Southern Literature Festival Association. He was a member of the American Association of University Professors, the Modern Language Association, Phi Delta Kappa, and Omicron Delta Kappa.
Professor Young married Arlease Lewis in 1941, and the couple had two sons, Thomas Daniel and Terry Lewis. Dr. Young died in Bay Springs, Mississippi January 29, 1997.
- Correspondence--- Incoming---Brooks-Willis (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Manuscript---The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate---Typescript---Register and Table of Contents (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Manuscript---The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate---Xerox copy of Typescript---Pp. 1-133 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Manuscript---The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate---Xerox copy of typescript---Pp. 134-229 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Manuscript---The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate---Xerox copy of typescript---Pp. 229-317 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Manuscript---The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate---Xerox copy of typescript---Pp. 319-409 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Manuscript---The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate---Xerox copy of typescript---Pp. 410-520 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Manuscript---The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate---Xerox copy of typescript---Pp. 521-638 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Manuscript---The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate---Incomplete typewritten ms. with corrections (title page, acknowledgements, Foreword, contents, footnotes (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Printers Proof---First---Corrected---The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Printers Proof---Editor’s Copy---The Literary Correspondence of Daniel Davidson and Allen Tate (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Printers Proof--- First---The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate, Pp. vii-154 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Printers Proof---First---The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate, Pp. 155-442 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Printers Proof---House Set---The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson and Allen Tate (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Printers Proof---Miscellaneous Pages–The Literary Correspondence of Donald Davidson Tate and Allen Tate (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Manuscript---Gentle man in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 3 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 4 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 5 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 6 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 7 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 8 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 9 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 10 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 11 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 12 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 13 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Chapter 14 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Longhand copy---Footnotes (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 3 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 4 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 5 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 6 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 7 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 8 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 9 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 10 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 11 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 12 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 13 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Chapter 14 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Typescript---Footnotes and Afterword (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Corrected typescript---Preface, Chapters 1 and 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Corrected typescript---Chapters 3-5 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Corrected typescript---Chapters 6-7 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Corrected typescript---Chapters 8-9 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Corrected typescript---Chapters 10-11 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Corrected typescript---Chapters 12-13 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Corrected typescript---Chapter 14 and Epilogue (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Corrected typescript---Footnotes (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Corrected typescript---Footnotes (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Xerox copy of edited typescript---Chapters 1-2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Xerox copy of edited typescript---Chapters 2-3, partial copies (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Xerox copy of edited typescript---Chapters 3-4 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Xerox copy of edited typescript---Chapters 3-4 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Xerox copy of edited typescript---Chapters 5-6 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Xerox copy of edited typescript---Chapters 7-8 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Xerox copy of edited typescript---Chapters 9-10 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Xerox copy of edited typescript---Chapter 9, partial copy (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Xerox copy of edited typescript---Chapters 11-12 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Xerox copy of edited typescript---Chapters 13-14 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat----Xerox copy of edited typescript---Footnotes, Ch. 1-14 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Printers copy (page proofs)---Chapters 1-6 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Printers copy (page proofs)---Chapters 7-14, Footnotes (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Proof copy---Chapters 1-2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Proof copy---Chapters 3-4 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Proof copy---Chapters 5-6 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Proof copy---Chapters 7-8 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Proof copy---Chapters 9-10 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Proof copy---Chapters 11-12 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Proof copy---Chapters 13-14 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Manuscript---Gentleman in a Dustcoat---Proof copy---Footnotes (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Typescript---Introduction (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Typescript---A Critic Almost Anonymous: John Crowe Ransom Goes North by Louis D. Rubin, Jr. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Typescript---The Evolution of Ransom’s Critical Theory, Image, and Idea by Thomas D. Young (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Typescript---The Pedagogue as Critic by Hugh Kenner (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Typescript---The Linguistic Moment in “The Wreck of the Deutschland” by J. Hillis Miller (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Typescript---On Literary Form by Kenneth Burke (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Xerox copy of typescript of edited typescript---Foreword and Introduction by Crump, Klein, Sharp and Young (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Xerox copy of edited typescript---A Critic Almost Anonymous: John Crowe Ransom Goes North by Louis D. Rubin, Jr. (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Manuscript---The Hew Criticism and After---Xerox copy of edited typescript---The Evolution of Ransom’s Critical Theory, Image and Idea by Thomas D. Young (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Xerox copy of edited typescript---The Pedagogue as Critic by Hugh Kenner (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Xerox copy of edited typescript---The Linguistic Moment in “The Wreck of the Deutschland” by J. Hillis Miller (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Xerox copy of edited typescript---On a Shift in the Concept of Interpretation by Ralph Cohen (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Xerox copy of edited typescript---On Literary Form by Kenneth Burke (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Proofs---Foreword and Introduction by Crump, Klein, Sharp and Young (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Proofs---A Critic Almost Anonymous: John Crowe Ransom Goes North by Louis D. Rubin, Jr. (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Proofs---The Evolution of Ransom’s Critical Theory, Image and Idea by Thomas D. Young (4 copies) (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Proofs---The Pedagogue as Critic by Hugh Kenner (4 copies) (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Proofs---The Linguistic Moment in “The Wreck of the Deutschland” by J. Hillis Miller (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Proofs---On a Shift in the Concept of Interpretation by Ralph Cohen (4 copies) (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Manuscript---The New Criticism and After---Proofs---On Literary Form by Kenneth Burke (4 copies) (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Manuscript--- Article---A Little Divergence: The Critical Theories of John Crowe Ransom and Cleanth Brooks (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---Ella C. Ransom/Various correspondents (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---J.J. Ransom/Ella C. Ransom (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---J.J. Ransom/John Crowe Ransom (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---J.J. Ransom/Various correspondents (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---R.P. Ransom/J.J. Ransom (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Richard Blackmur (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Cleanth Brooks (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Chancellor Carmichael (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Donald Davidson (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Robert Duncan (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/T.S. Eliot (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Research materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Robert Graves (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Chancellor James Kirkland (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Andrew Lytle (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/ F.O. Matthiesson (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/ Edwin Mims (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Christopher Morley (Box 9, Folder 20)
- Research materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/George Marion O’Donnell (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Philip Rahv (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/ Annie Ransom (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/ Ella Ransom, 1911-1914 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Ella C. Ransom, 1917-1918 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Ella C. Ransom, 1936-1939 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/ Ellene Ransom, 1911-1939 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/J.J. Ransom, 1911-1914 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/J.J. Ransom, 1917-1918 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Newton P. Stallworth (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/ Wallace Stevens (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Randall Stewart (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1922-1924 (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1926-1929 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1931-1932 (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1933-1935 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crown Ransom/Allen Tate, 1936-1937 (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 19)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 21)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 22)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 23)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1943-1944 (Box 10, Folder 24)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1945-1946 (Box 10, Folder 25)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1947-1949 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1953-1959 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Allen Tate, 1960-1967 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Lionel Trilling (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Louis Untermeyer (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Robert Penn Warren, 1930-1944 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Robert Penn Warren, 1945-1971 (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Thomas D. Young (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Various correspondents, A-N (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/Various correspondents, O-Z (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies of correspondence---John Crowe Ransom/and others---correspondence on the finances of Kenyon Review (Box 11, Folder 14)
- Research Materials---Xerox copies---Various items concerning John Crowe Ransom’s finances, position, etc. (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Research Materials---Essays by John Crowe Ransom (Box 11, Folder 16)